French Literature mss., LMC 1391 LMC 1391
Lilly Library
- French Literature mss.
  - Carco, Francis, 1886-1958, novelist, poet. 79, Quai D'Orsay, Paris, France. To "mon cher Reboul". Discusses his scenario "La Femme traquée" and the financial arrangments for its production. A.L.S., 1935 Oct 3; 2 p. 27 cm.
    Letter bordered in black.
    Removed from Carco, L'equipe, Paris, Émile-Paul Fréres, 1919 (PQ2605 .A55E64). 1974
  - Crommelynck, Fernand, 1886-1970, playwright. 28 Bd. Victor Hugo, Neuilly sur Seine, France. To Charles Spaak. 10 Rue Ernest de Loison, Neuily, France. Would like to discuss an important and urgent matter with him. Requests that he call as soon as possible. A.L.S., 1937 May 27; 1 p. 19 cm.
    Removed from Crommelynck, Les amants Puérils. Paris: Aux Editions de la Sirène, 1921 (Lilly PQ2605 .R76A77). 1983
  - Jouhandeau, Marcel?, 1888-1979, author. To Mon cher Poupet. Asks him to decide on the subject of restricted revision of the manuscript which he had given to Poupet. A.L.S., 1937 July 3; 2 p. 21 cm.
    Signed: Jouhandeau.
    Written in an unidentified hand.
    Removed from Marcel Jouhandeau, Un Monde, Paris: Gallinard, 1950 (Lilly PQ2619 .O76U5). 1977
  - Masson, André, 1900-, author. Quinsac, Gironde, France. To André Girodie, Paris, France. Thanking him for his letter, a catalogue of an exposition, and information concerning Nicolas Beaujon. A.L.S., 1941 Aug 15; 2 p. 18 cm.
    Accompanied by: 1) Cover; 2) Notes relating to Nicolas Beaujon. 8 p. 4-15 cm.; 3) Portraits of Nicolas Beaujon.
    Removed from André Masson's Un Mécène Bordelais, Nicolas Beaujon, 1718-1786… Bordeaux, Delmas, 1937. 1951
  - Gaulle, Charles de, 1890-1970, pres. of France. 4 Carlton Gardens, S.W.I., [London, England]. To [Sir Harold George] Nicolson. "…je viens seulement de lire l'article que vous avez publié dans la revue 'Spectator'." A.L.S., 1942 Sept. 28; 2 p. 25.5 cm.
    Accompanied by typed transcription and translation.
    Gift. 1985
  - Postcard to Monsieur L Dieudonne concerning "...quelques exemplaires... que 'L 'Enclos' aujourd'hui ou d'autres de l'epoque 1900, en vie d'une etude que vous ... sur des publications...". Postcard in response to Diedonne's request of last November, not signed. Verso bears printed drawing of Charles Louis Philippe (1874-1909) by Charles Guerin in 1904 with facsimile signature., 1943 Jun 15; 1 p. 10.5 cm.
    Removed from Philippe, Quatre histoires de pauvre amour, Editions de L'Enclos, 1897 (Lilly PQ2631.H5 Q2) 1979
  - La Tour du Pin, Patrice de, 1911-, poet. Le Bignon-Mirabeau, Loiret, France. To Jacques Collin Delavaud. 86 Boulevard Malesherbe, Paris, France. Writes that he won't be able to come to Paris before spring. Sends him wishes to Jäis and to all his friends at La Tortue. A.L.S., 1944 Feb. 29; 2 p. 21 cm.
    Accompanied by envelope from which date and place are noted.
    Removed from Patrice de La Tour du Pin, La quête de joie, Paris: La Tortue, 1933 (Lilly PQ2623 .A679 Q5). 1977
  - Gide, André Paul Guillaume, 1869-1951, author. 14, Rue Michelet, Algiers. To [Pierre de Lanux]. "Au sujet de la publication dans Carrefour…j'ai correspondon avec Boutelleau … pour ce même Carrefour un article de Christian Megret…"; mention of his article Justice et Charité. A.L.S., 1945 Feb. 5; 1 p. 27 cm.
    Removed from Gide, Journal, 1939-1942… Paris, Gallimard, 1946 (Lilly PQ2613 .I2Z53 1946). 1975
  - Giono, Jean, 1895-1970, novelist. To "Chère Anna". Concerned about the malady of leprosy. A.L.S., 1946 Jan 6; 2 p. 27 cm.
    Letter concludes with the names of Adrene de Spinetta and Docteur Bernard Spinetta, 22 Rue de France 22, Nice. A.M.
    Removed from Giono, Les Âmes Fortes. Paris, Gallimard, 1949 (Lilly PQ2613 .I57A52). 1983
  - Giono, Jean, 1895-1970, author. To [Jean] Denoël. He speaks with deep affection of Adrienne Monnier and Sylvia Beach, about his farm, and about working on his books and poems. A.L.S., 1946 Feb 24; 2 p. 20 cm.
    In black ink on yellow paper.
    Removed from Giono, Rondeur des jours… Alger: Editions "Les vraies richesses", 1936 (Lilly PQ2613 .I57R77). 1977
  - Sartre, Jean-Paul, 1905-1980, author. The respectful prostitute… Translated and adapted by Eva Wolas. D., 1947?; [2], 42 p. 28 cm.
    Mimeo with extensive pencil corrections and annotations in an unknown hand.
    Title page has stamp of Frieda Fishbein, authors' representative.
    The Wolas version was first performed at New Stages Theatre, Feb. 9, 1948.
    Transfer. Book Department, Lilly Library. 1986
  - Cayla, Robert, bookseller. 28, Rue Saint-Sulpice, Paris 6e. To Maitre Yves Breton, Notaire, 15 rue Armand de Pontmartin à Avignon (Vaucluse). Discusses the receipt of the manuscript of Henri Perruchot's work, its price and textual problems. Encloses a letter of Perruchot. A.L.S., 1950 Jan 6; 1 p. 20 cm.
    Written on fold-over stationary of Librairie Robert Cayla.
    Enclosure: Henri Perruchot, 1917-, author. 26, Rue St Louis en l'Isle, Paris (IVe). To Robert Cayla. 3/1-1950. Relates problems with a portion of the manuscript of Epiphanisme. A.L.S. 1 p. 27 cm.
    With the letter is page 10 of the manuscript of "Introduction à l'Epiphanisme," n.d. A.D., 2 p. 22.3 cm. In blue and red ink with many emendations. Written on verso of a printed notice for a meeting, Mardi 15 Mars, of l'Internationale Des Jeunes Contre La Guerre. Published on pages 26-27 of "Introduction…"
    Removed from Perruchot, Introduction à l'Epipanisme. Paris, Le Sillage, 1949 (Lilly B817 .P4) which is inscribed by Perruchot to Yves Breton. 1985
  - Giono, Jean, 1895-1970, author, et al. Manosque, Basses Alpes, France. To Jean Denoël, 16, rue de Bourgogne, Paris VIIe. "On a bien parlé de vous et bien pensé a vous aujourhui avec Buffet et [Bergé?]." A. card S., 1950 June 17; 9 cm.
    Signed also with a message from "siene" and the signature of Bernard Buffet.
    Removed from Giono, Rondeur des jours… Alger: Editions "Les vraies richessess," 1936 (Lilly PQ2613 .I57R77). 1977
  - [Bosco], Henri, 1888-1976, poet, educator, novelist. Rabat, Morocco. To M. De Noel, Editeur. Series of questions beginning: Où êtes vous? ApcS., 1950 Oct 1; 2 p. 10.7 cm.
    Signed: Henri & Madeleine.
    Written in green ink on picture postcard of Van Gogh's Sailing Boats at Les Saintes-Maries.
    Addressee in pencil on picture side of card.
    Removed from Bosco, Des sables à la mer: pages marocaines. Paris, Gallimard, 1950 (Lilly PQ2603 .O626D44). 1985
  - Jouhandeau, Marcel, 1888-1979, author. To [Paul Charles Jules] Robert. Writes of coming to visit the next day and staying overnight. "Mon livre Élise architecte est sorti." A.L.S., 1951?; 2 p. 21 cm.
    Dated: Vendredi.
    Addressed to "Mon cher petite Robert."
    Removed from Marcel Jouhandeau, Élise architecte, Paris: B. Grasset, 1951 (Lilly PQ2619 .O76 E42 1951). 1977
  - Cocteau, Jean, 1889-1963, author. To Norbert O. Meissner, Pension Briechle, Moorweidenstrasse 34, Hamburg 13. Friendly personal letter. A.L.S., 1952 July 25; 1 p. 27 cm.
    Accompanied by cover and three photographs.
    Purchase. 1970
  - Cauda, Patrice, 1925-, poet. To trés cher. "Voila le travail, est-ce bien comme ça?" A.L.S., 1954 Jan 12; 1 p. 27 cm.
    Dated Mardi, with 13-1-54 in pencil in upper right hand corner, as a received date, in another hand.
    Removed from Cauda, Domaine inachevé: poemes. Paris: J. Aubanel et son Frère, 1954 (Lilly PQ2605 A.58 D66), no. 1 of 12 numbered copies. 1977
  - Les deux scandales de Panama [by Jean Bouvier: correspondence, etc.] T.Ls.S., 1963 Sept. 25-Oct 9; 2 p. 27 cm.
    Contents: 1) Letters to Jean Bouvier, 1920-, professor à la Sorbonne, from Jean Falaize, 25 Sept. 1963, carbon of T.L., and from Jules Marie Priou, 9 Oct. 1963, T.L.S., concerning illustrations for Bouvier, Les deux scandales de Panama. 2) Photograph, copy, of M. et. Mme. Cornélius Herz, published between pages 112-113 of Les deux scandales… Rene Juilliard, Paris, 1964 (Main HE537.3 .B783). 3) Tracé du canal, printed, from Supplément au Bulletin du Canal Interocéanique, No. 69, 1er Juillet 1882.
    Transferred from Lilly Library Book Department, acquired with the M. Fontane purchase of 1982 from G. Sabbagh, Paris. 1985
  - Ribemont-Dessaignes, Georges, 1884-, author. Saint Jeannet Alpes-Martines, France. To Valentine Hugo. Writes of having the flu and seeing one of Hugo's works, which he liked. "…et me rend de la jeuness, cette jeuness qu'un justement n'a cessé d'être la votre." A.L.S., 1965 May 1; 2 p. 21 cm.
    Removed from Jacques Prévert, Georges, Cagnes: [s.n.], 1965 (Lilly PQ2631 .R387 G34). 1977
  - Fannière, Edith, binder. To Timothy d'Arch Smith. Writes of buying copies of "L'instinct de bonheur" which could be found at a bookstore on the right bank; of rebinding a copy of "L'Oracle" and mentions technicalities of keeping the format intact. A.L.S., 1969 Mar 4; 3 p. 24 cm.
    In dark blue ink on one sheet of blue paper and one of white.
    Removed from Roger Peyrefitte, L'Oracle, Paris: Jean Vigneau, 1948 (Lilly PQ2631 .E915 O63). 1977
  - Fannière, Edith, binder. To Timothy d'Arch Smith. Received "la Nature du Prince" and is rebinding it in light gray; "La Batarde" is coming along, it is being bound in morocco leather and leather the same as for L'Oracle. A.L.S., 1969 July 22; 1 p. 21 cm.
    In blue ink on white paper.
  - Autrand, Charles, fl. 1969, poet. Amerika (1966). A.D.S., 1 p. 27 cm.
    Fifteen lines of verse published on page 58 of Autrand, La peine de vivre… 1969
    Removed from Aurand, La peine de vivre, Paris, Libraire Saint-Germain-des-Prés, 1969 (Lilly PQ2661 .U85P37) 1974
  - Frannière, Edith, binder. To [Timothy] d'Arch Smith. Mentions letter sent with two books, bound in morocco leather; writes of binding some books with photographic montage and learning restoration of old books. A.L.S., 1970 July 3; 2 p. 24 cm.
    In blue ink on blue paper.
    Removed from Roger Peyrefitte, La fin des ambassades, Paris: Flammarion, 1953 (Lilly PQ2631 .E915 F49). 1977
  - Milorad, poet. To Cher ami. Refers to the self-portrait of Cocteau. Brenner proposes on the suggestion of Roger Vigny "de faire une matinée de France-Culture sur Cocteau…" A.L.S., 1975 Feb 25; 1 p. 29.5 cm.
    Paper watermarked with fleur-de-lis surrounded by St. Louis (PSL).
    Removed from Cocteau, Lettres à Milorad. Paris, Éditions Saint-Germain-des-Pres, 1975 (Lilly PQ2605 .O15Z5 1975). 1979
  - Berger, Anne, 1951-, poet. la loi blanche. A.D.S., 1975?; 1 p. 20.5 cm.
    Written on p. [3].
    Fair copy of poem published on p. 7.
    In Berger, La Loi blanche. Paris: Librairie Saint-Germain-des-Prés, 1975. (Lilly PQ2662 .E6614 L83) 1987
  - Brindeau, Serge, 1925-, poet, editor. Harmonie bouge. A.D.S., 1975?; 7 p. 21-30 cm.
    Draft of poem with corrections and alterations in ink, pencil, and felt-tip.
    Only p. 4 is 21 cm.
    Accompanied by orginal collage by Alix Haxthausen, D.S., ca. 1975, 18.5x25 cm.
    Removed from Brindeau, Harmonie bouge; gravures de Alix Haxthausen. G.D., 1975 (Lilly PQ2662 .R556 H28). 1986
  - Clément, Line, poet. Déjà les ailes sont noires Tu seras la fourmi au trombone… A.D.S., 1976 Mar.; 1 p. 14 cm.
    Last two lines, with illustrations, from the poem "La panoplie de la parfaite petite ménagère" in À la fenêtre d'une chiromancienne bègue.
    Removed from Clément, À la fenêtre d'une chicomancienne bègue. Paris: Librairie Saint Germain-des-Prés, 1974 (Lilly PQ2663 .L55A12), no. 33 of 40 numbered copies. 1977
  - Zaborski, Frédéric, 1955-, poet. Chansons d'enfant… [first line of poem]. A.D.S., 1977 Sept. 23; 1 leaf 14 cm.
    Poem of 18 lines in blue ink.
    Date and signature on verso.
    Removed from Frédéric Zaborski, Cercueil de rêves, Paris: Editions Saint-Germain-des-Prés, 1974 (Lilly PQ2686 .A15C42) 1977
  - Ackermann, Louise Victorine Choquet, 1813-1890, poet. La France saigne encor; qu'elle se tranquillise [first line]. A.D.S., undated.; 1 p. 10.2 cm.
    Removed from, but not published in, Ackermann, Poésies philosophiques. Nice: Caisson et Mignon, 1871 (Lilly PQ2152 .A24 P74). 1991
  - Antoine, André, 1858-1943, theatre manager, author. To Ernest Renan. Asks Renan to let him produce L'abesse de Jouarre as a play at the Theatre-Libre. Makes reference to Emile Zola, Théodore de Banville, Alphonse Daudet, comte Tolstoi, Jean Richepin, Emile Bergerat, Henry Becque, and others. A.L.S., undated.; 4 p. 22 cm.
    In red ink with corrections.
    Watermark: Oriental Paper (with emblematic device).
    Removed from Ernest Renan, L'abesse de Jouarre, Paris: Calmann Lévy, 1886 (Lilly PQ2386 .R37A6). 1978
  - Augier, Émile, 1820-1889, dramatist. 43, Rue de Clichy. To "mon cher poète." Note of thanks. A.L.S., undated.; [2] p. 6 cm.
    On black-bordered calling card of Augier.
    Removed from Augier, Madame Caverlet: piece en quatre actes, en prose. Paris: Calmann Levy, 1876 (Lilly PQ2154 .A6 M17 1876). 1991
  - Badin, Georges, 1941-, poet. l'arbre des l'enfance… [first line of poem]. A.D., undated.; 1 p. 31 cm.
    Seven lines of poetry in ink.
    Removed from Badin, Places. Tarn, France: Gaston Puel, 1968 (Lilly PQ2662 .A32 P69). 1977
  - Badin, Georges, 1941-, poet. de l'eau trainée… [first line of poem]. A.D., undated.; 1 p. 31 cm.
    Three lines of poetry in ink.
    Removed from George Badin, Places. Tarn, France: Gaston Puel, 1968 (Lilly PQ2662 .A32 P69). 1977
  - Becque, Henri François, 1837-1899, dramatist. To "Chere Madam". Regrets that he is unable to accept her kind invitation. A.L.S., undated.; 1 p. 18 cm.
    Paper watermarked Original Andward Mill.
    Removed from Becque, L'enfant prodigue… Paris, Michel Lévy Frères, 1868 (Lilly PQ2193 .B4E56). 1974
  - Becque, Henri François, 1837-1899, dramatist. To "Ma chere amie". He is concerned about the health of his friend. A.L.S., undated.; 3 p. 18 cm.
    Removed from Becque, L'enfant prodigue … Paris, Michel Lévy Frères, 1868 (Lilly PQ2193 .B4E56). 1974
  - Becque, Henri François, 1837-1899, dramatist. To "Ma chere amie". Mentions Anatole Claveau and Victorien Sardou. A.L.S., undated.; 1 p. 17 cm.
    Paper watermarked Original Debils Mills.
  - Bernard, Tristan, 1866-1947, dramatist. To Cher Ubu. Mentions that Léon Blum is coming to dinner and that he (Tristan) would like to see the play La Cloche Engloutie by Gernhardt Hauptmann. A.L.S., undated.; 1 p. 18 cm.
    Dated: Jeudi.
    In pencil on verso: à Maurice Donnay.
  - Bernard, Tristan, 1866-1947, dramatist. To mon cher ami. Extends invitation for dinner on Friday, with friends Léon Blum and his wife. "Madame B[------] me charge de toutes ses amitiés, pour vous et Madame Ubu.", undated.
  - Bernstein, Henri, 1876-1953, dramatist. Winter Palace, Nice-Cimiez. To Marcelle Geniat. Complimentary remarks and an invitation to lunch at the hotel. T.L.S., undated.; 1 p. 18 cm.
    Dated November 19.
    Removed from Bernstein, Le Venin. Paris, Librairie Arthème Fayard, 1938 (Lilly PQ2603 .E65V46). 1974
  - Berthollet, Claude Louis, comte, 1748-1822. Note. Refers to a small volume on bleaching. A. note S., undated.; 1 p. 13 cm.
    Removed from Berthollet's Essai de statique chirnique …Paris, Firmin Didot, 1803. 2v. (Lilly QD501 .B54). 1956
  - Bloy, Ernest Henri Marc, 1846-1917, author. [Ici on assassine les grands hommes]. A.D., undated.; 2 p. 18 cm.
    Text begins: Voila dix ans qui il est enterré, le pauvre Hello!... with holograph corrections and variations from the printed work.
    Incomplete.
    Accompanied by three pages of notes, A.Ds., 16 and 22 cm.
    Bound in Bloy, Ici on assassine … Paris, Du Mercvre de France, 1895 (Lilly PQ2198 .B18I16).
  - Campan, Mme Jeanne Louise Henriette (Genet), (Mme Pierre Dominique François Berthollet dit Campan), 1752-1822, educator, first lady of the bedchamber to Marie Antoinette. To Monsieur. Speaks of her brother, of "Citoyen Dufay" and of the minister of war. A.L.S., undated.; 1 leaf 24 cm.
    Date illegible but it may be "Ce 25 pluv: anno 1" or 1793, Feb. 13.
  - Cauda, Patrice, 1925-, poet. [Domaine inachevé: poemes]. A.D.S., undated.; 8 leaves 23.5 cm.
    Contains 8 of the 12 poems published in Cauda, Comine inachevé: 1) Né sous une étoile sans nom… 2) Sur quelle route… 3) Mon amour comme une argile… 4) Les rochers surplombent mon corps… 5) Longtemp l'heur va-t-elle tourner… 6) Au bout du monde un homme… 7) Quelle voix m'appelle dans le lointain… 8) Quelle étoile s'attendrira…
    Each poem in ink on deckle-edged paper, signed with the full name of the poet.
    Removed from Cauda, Domaine inachevé: poèmes. Paris: J. Aubanel et Son Frère, 1954 (Lilly PQ2605 .A7973 D66), no. 1 of 12 numbered copies. 1977
  - Chabert, Pierre, poet. Gode. A.D.S., undated.; 1 p. 27 cm.
    Poem of 12 lines in ink.
    Published in Chabert, Les sales bêtes, page 28
    Removed from Chabert, Les sales bêtes. Paris: Poésie-Club, 1968 (Lilly PQ2605 .H21 S16), copy U of 26 copies. 1977
  - Claretie, Jules, 1840-1913, author. Viroflay, Seine-et-Oise, France. To "Chére Madame et Amie." Revision. A.L.S., undated.; 1 p. 17 cm.
  - Cocteau, Jean, 1889-1963, author. To André Paysan. Inquires of his friend's silence and comments on their joint work, "le gros monsieur en deuil." A.L.S., undated.; 2 p. 18 cm.
    Written in ink across two contiguous pages.
    Accompanied by stamped envelope from which recipient's name is derived; postmark undecipherable.
    Purchase. 1979
  - Cocteau, Jean, 1889-1963, author. To André Paysan, 9 rue Frochot 9, Paris. Comments on their exchange of letters and mentions their joint work as "le vieux monsieur en deuil". A.L.S., undated.; 2 p. 20 cm.
    Accompanied by stamped envelope from which recipient's name is derived; postmark dated may be: 4-9-12.
  - Cocteau, Jean, 1889-1963, author and André Paysan, playwright. Le gros Monsieur en deuil. Piece en un Acte par André Paysan et Jean Cocteau. A.D.S., undated.; 22 p. 31 cm. (Foliobox 7)
    Cover page illustrated with figure of obese man drawn in ink.
    Cast of characters given on verso of title page.
    First 12 pages of text in ink appear to be in the hand of Paysan.
    Last 6 unnumbered pages in ink with other lines in pencil on verso of last 2 pages appear to be in the hand of Cocteau.
    Accompanied by former binding in purple boards with leather spine; title and authors' names in gold.
  - Colette, Sidonie Gabrielle, 1873-1954, novelist. To Madame Mimi Carter, 7 rue Mesnil, Paris. "J'ai encore bien mal a le jambe…" A. card S., undated.; 9 cm.
    Accompanied by cover, postmarked from the Department of Isere.
    Removed from Colette, Sido, Paris, J. Ferenczi & Fils, 1930 (Lilly PQ2605 O28S56 1930). 1973
  - Coppée, François, 1842-1908, poet, playwright. To Madame. Approves the recipient's scheme for the domestic education of young women. A.L.S., undated.; 2 p. 18 cm.
    Several phrases are blacked out.
  - Coupon, Gérard, 1953-, poet. douleur rase. A.D.S., undated.; 1 p. 14 cm.
    Poem of 14 lines written in blue ink.
    Removed from Coupon, Appel à la lézarde. Paris, Éditions Saint Germain-des-Prés, 1974 (Lilly PQ2663 O83 A64), no. 11 of 40 numbered copies. 1977
  - Courteline, Georges, 1858-1929, dramatist, author. To "cher ami." Apologizes for not receiving his letter sooner, and grants his request. A.L.S., undated.; 1 p. 18.3 cm.
    Removed from Courteline, Les femmes d'amis. Paris: C. Marpon et E. Flammarion, 1888 (Lilly PQ2605 .O7677 F32). 1982
  - Daudet, Alphonse, 1840-1897, author. 18 rue de Vorges, Paris. To Mon cher confrère. Feels obliged to address the second volume of theater to him. A.N.S., undated.; 1 leaf 15.5 cm.
    Removed from L'évangéliste: roman parisien, Paris: E. Dentu, 1883 (Lilly PQ2216 .E9 copy 2). 1977
  - Delille, Jacques Montanier, 1738-1813, poet. To L'abbe Bertin. Planinville, Normandie, France. Apologizes for not writing more frequently. Discusses a letter Bertin wrote to Voltaire. A.L.S., undated.; [2] p. 23.5 cm.
  - Delteil, Joseph, 1894-1978, author. Pieusse (Aude), France. To "Cher ami." Discusses the release and promotion of his new book. A.L.S., undated.; [3] p. 9 & 17 cm.
    Page [1] on postcard: Vallée de l'Aude, Défilé de St-Georges, Près Anat, Sortie des Gorges et l'Usine Électrique.
  - Delteil, Joseph, 1894-1978, author. Pieusse (Aude), France. To "Mon cher ami." Discusses financial arrangements for the German translation of his Don Juan. Will not be returning to Paris. A.L.S., undated.; 1 p. 13.7 cm.
    On postcard: Vallée de l'Aude, Péler-Nage de Notre-Dame de Marceille, Près l'Moux - La Vierge.
  - Delzant, Alidor, 1848-1905, literary critic. To "Mon cher ami." Goncourt has entrusted him to deliver "le précieux volume" with the second prèface not printed on Japon. His own work with a chapter on Philippe Burty is under way. A.L.S., undated.; 1 p. 13.5 cm.
    In ink on gray paper.
    Delzant's own work, Les Goncourt, with pages 240-254 on Burty, was published in Paris in 1889 (Main PQ2261 .Z5D3).
    Removed from Edmond de Goncourt, Germinie Lacerteux (with the Second Preface). Paris, Charpentier, 1888 (Lilly PQ2261 .G375) which is inscribed by Goncourt to Burty. 1982
  - Deville, Michel, poet. [Poèmes Zinopinés: three poems]. D., undated.; 3 p. 29.8 cm.
    In ink in an unidentified hand.
    Poem titles: Le vieil âne et l'amer; Amour fou; La vache.
    Published on pages 7-8, 60, 99, of the work from which they were removed.
    Accompanied by photograph of an unidentified man, presumably Deville.
    Removed from Deville, Poèmes Zinopinés. Paris, Editions Saint-Germain-des Prés, 1972 (Lilly PQ2664 .E8P74). 1984
  - Du Bouchet, André, 1924-, author. Ici en deux. A.D.S., undated.; [36] p. 34x25.5 cm. (Foliobox 7)
    Illustrated by two drawings in blue pencil by Geneviève Asse, one of which is signed.
    Two minor variations from the published text.
    Removed from De Bouchet, Ici en deux. Genève, Quentin, 1982 (Lilly PQ2664 .U288I16). 1982
  - Dumas, Alexandre, 1802-1870, author. To Alphonse Millaud. Recommends the son of a mutual acquaintance to cover courses at the Sorbonne for one of Millaud's newspappers. A.L.S., undated.; 1 p. 21.5 cm.
    Dated: 20 juillet.
    Removed from Alexandre Dumas, Impressions de voyage. Paris, Revue des Deux Mondes, 1834 (Lilly PQ2227 I4 1834). 1980
  - Dumas, Alexandre, 1824-1895, novelist, playwright. To Charles de La Roûnat. Mentions his friend's last letter and poses certain philosophical questions. A.L.S., undated.; 6 p. 20.5 cm.
    Addressed to "Cher Ami."
    Recipient's identification based on pencilled name.
    Watermark: L-JDL&Ce.
    Removed from Vol. 1 of Dumas, Théatre Complet, 8 vols. Paris, Calmann Lévy, 1890 (Lilly PQ2231 .A19 1890). 1979
  - Dumas, Alexandre, 1824-1895, novelist, playwright. To Léodile Bera de Champceix. Offers criticism on the author's play in three acts. A.L.S., undated.; 8 p. 18 cm.
    Addressed to "Madame."
    Recipient's identification based on penciled name.
    Watermark: JO[?]NSON 1864.
  - Dumas, Alexandre, 1824-1895, novelist, playwright. To Mon cher ami. Mentions his daughter Jeannine Dumas and his home. A.L.S., undated.; 4 p. 15.5 cm.
    Watermark: TREASURY.
  - Dumas, Alexandre, 1824-1895, novelist, playwright. To Monsieur. Mentions La Dame aux Camélias, the Vaudeville, Déjazet, and M. de Beaufort. A.L.S., undated.; 4 p. 18 cm.
    Embossed circle, 1.3 cm., in upper left corner bears words Extra Superfine with small floral design in center.
  - Estaunié, Édouard, 1862-1942, author. To Monsieur. Comments on the accomplishments of Genevieve Rostan who is a woodcut artist of genunine talent. A.L.S., undated.; 2 p. 18 cm.
    Stationery bordered in black.
    Accompanied by two wood-cut illustrations by Rostan which were used for L'infirme aux mains de lumière by Estaunié published by Ferenczi in 1925.
    Removed from Estaunié, L'infirme aux mains de lumière. Paris, B. Grasset, 1923 (Lilly PQ2609 .S8I43). 1985
  - L'Eternel fatigué… sur la terre. A.D., undated.; 1 p. 16 cm.